let set11 =
    [
        {
            question: `#1. In India, crops are classified into two groups, on the basis of the season they grow-Rabi crops and Kharif crops. In the context of these crops, consider the following statements: \n 1. Kharif crops are sown in summer. \n 2. Rabi crops are grown in winter. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                ['A. 1 only',
                    'B. 2 only',
                    'C. Both 1 and 2',
                    'D. Neither 1 nor 2',

                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: kharif crops are sown during the monsoon (June to September), and not in summer. Rice, corn, soybean, groundnut, cotton, etc. are Kharif crops. Rabi crops are grown in winter. Wheat, chickpea, pea, mustard, flax are examples of Rabi crops.Apart from this, several pulses and vegetables are grown in the summer season, in many places.`
        },
        {
            question: `#2. With regard to organic manure, consider the following statements: \n 1. It enhances the water holding capacity of the soil. \n 2. It makes the soil loose and porous. \n 3. It enhances the number of friendly microbes. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
            options:
                ['A. 1 only',
                    'B. 1 and 2 only',
                    'C. 2 and 3 only',
                    'D. 1, 2 and 3',

                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Organic manure is better than chemical fertilizers. While organic manure enhances the water holding capacity of the soil, makes the soil porous and loose, and increases the number of friendly microbes; prolonged use of chemical fertilizers decline the soil fertility and also cause water pollution. Chemicals are used as pesticides and weedicides as well. 2, 4 D is an example of weedicide. The chemicals present in these increase the chemical content of the soil.`
        },
        {
            question: `#3. Cod liver oil contains high amount of vitamin D. From which of the following animals, is cod liver oil obtained?`,
            options:
                ['A. Frog',
                    'B. Fish',
                    'C. Snake',
                    'D. None of these',

                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: Cod liver oil is obtained from fishes. It is abundant in vitamin A and D. It is also rich in other nutrients.`
        },
        {
            question: `#4. Which one of the following is a preservative used in preservation of fruits as jams and jellies?`,
            options:
                ['A. Mustard oil',
                    'B. Vinegar',
                    'C. Sugar',
                    'D. All the above',

                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: SUGAR and Citric Acid (Lemon Juice) are the main preservativesThe product is preserved by lowering the water activity by cooking the fruit (evaporating water) in a very high sugar concentration. Acid helps by lowering the pHAfter the jam is ready it is hot-filled to a clean jar, which is sterilized by the heat from the jam. The inversion of the jars helps by sterilizing the lid. Vinegar contains acetic acid, it is perfectly suited to preserve foods. It works because most of microorganisms responsible to destroying food cannot live in an acetic acid environment. Preservation is probably the most common reason vinegar is used in food preparation. The use of mustard oil or vinegar prevents the spoilage of fruits and vegetable because food-spoiling bacteria cannot live in such an environment. They are used as preservative for preserving fruits such as raw mango,amla and lemon in the form of their pickles.`
        },
        {
            question: `#5. Beans and peas are preferably grown in nitrogen deficient soil because: \n 1. They absorb most of the nitrogen from the soil. \n 2. They are leguminous plants. \n 3. They have rhizobium in root nodules which can fix atmospheric nitrogen. \n 4. They are green plants.`,
            options:
                ['A. 1 and 2',
                    'B. 2 and 3',
                    'C. 3 and 4',
                    'D. 1 and 4',

                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: Bean and Peas are leguminous plants. They fix nitrogen in the soil with the help of Rhizobium bacteria present in the root nodules of the plants.Thus, they fix nitrogen and replenish the deficiency of nitrogen in the soil. Therefore, farmers prefer to grow bean and peas in nitrogen deficient soil.`
        },
        {
            question: `#6. Which one of the following crops does not require nitrogenous fertiliser?`,
            options:
                ['A. Wheat',
                    'B. Millet',
                    'C. Beans',
                    'D. Paddy',

                ],
            answer: `Answer: C`,
            exp: `Explanation: Beans is legume crop.A legume crop does not require nitrogenous fertilizers because its roots have root nodules that have nitrogenous bacteria called Rhizobium. This bacteria fixes atmospheric nitrogen and the plants converts nitrogen into various nitrogenous compounds.`
        },
        {
            question: `#7. Which one of the following pairs is incorrect?`,
            options:
                ['A. Rust of wheat - fungi',
                    'B. Citrus canker - bacteria',
                    'C. Yellow vein mosaic - Virus',
                    'D. Aspergillosis -Bacteria',

                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: ``
        },
        {
            question: `#8. The process of loosening and turning the soil is called:`,
            options:
                ['A. Ploughing',
                    'B. Levelling',
                    'C. Manuring',
                    'D. All the above',

                ],
            answer: `Answer: A`,
            exp: `Explanation: The processing of loosening and turning the soil is called 'tilling' or 'ploughing' of the soil. It the the most important task in the field of agriculture. It is very important to loosen the soil because it allows the roots of the plants to penetrate deep into the soil. This provides roots the space to expand under the surface of the earth. The loosened soil helps in the growth of earthworms and microbes which add humus to the soil and increase the fertility. Loosening and turning the soil brings the nutrients to the top so that the plants can use them.`
        },
        {
            question: `#9. Which one among the following is a useful microorganism? \n 1. Salmonella typhi \n 2. Rhizobium \n 3. Lactobacillus \n 4. Rhinovirus`,
            options:
                ['A. 1 and 2',
                    'B. 2 and 3',
                    'C. 3 and 4',
                    'D. 1 and 4',

                ],
            answer: `Answer: B`,
            exp: `Explanation: Rhizobium are a group of Gram-negative soil bacteria \n that are well known for their symbiotic relationship with various \n leguminous (soybeans, alfalfa etc). Rhizobia are diazotrophic \n bacteria that fix nitrogen after becoming established inside the \n root nodules of legumes (Fabaceae). To express genes for nitrogen \n fixation, rhizobia require a plant host; they cannot independently fix \n nitrogen. In general, they are gram negative, motile, non-sporulating \n rods. \n Lactobacillus is a type of bacteria. There are lots of different \n species of lactobacillus bacteria. These are "friendly" bacteria that \n normally live in our digestive, urinary, and genital systems without \n causing disease. Lactobacillus is also in some fermented foods like \n yogurt and in dietary supplements.Lactobacillus is most commonly \n taken by mouth to treat and prevent diarrhea, including infectious \n diarrhea and diarrhea linked with using antibiotics. Some people also \n take lactobacillus by mouth for general digestion problems, irritable \n bowel syndrome (IBS), colic in babies, inflammatory bowel \n disease (IBD), inflammation of the colon, stomach pain, constipation, \n and many other conditions but there is no good scientific evidence to \n support many of these uses.`
        },
        {
            question: `#10. Which leaves are used to protect stored grains from insects and microorganisms?`,
            options:
                ['A. Mango leaves',
                    'B. Peepal leaves',
                    'C. Banana leaves',
                    'D. Neem leaves',

                ],
            answer: `Answer: D`,
            exp: `Explanation: Neem tree is native of India. Its leaves contain chemicals such as Nimbin which have antifungal, antibacterial property. Hence, dried neem leaves are used for storing food grains at home. Neem leaves kept in stored grain, protect from pests and microorganisms.`
        }
    ]